Oh, wait.
哦, 等等。
Alright.
好吧。
Alright, you're listening to radiolab.
好吧, 你正在听radiolab
Radio from W N Y ....
电台从W N Y ....
C
Hey, this is radiolab last year, a cyber attack disrupted the colonial pipeline ...
嘿, 这是radiolab去年, 网络攻击破坏了殖民地的管道......。
was a big year for cyber crime.
是网络犯罪的一个大年。
The FBI confirms it's investigating 100 different types of ransomware attacks.
联邦调查局证实它正在调查100种不同类型的勒索软件攻击。
According to the FBI, the amount of money taken by ransomware has gone up by more than 1000 percent over the past five years, and this got us t thinking about this episode we did on this new kind of crime way back in its relatively quaint early days (古朴的早期) in 2015 called Darkode.
根据联邦调查局的数据, 在过去的五年里, 勒索软件的金额上升了1000%以上, 这让我们想到了我们在2015年相对古朴的早期（古朴的早期）对这种新的犯罪方式所做的这一集, 叫做Darkode。
Hey, I'm Jad Abrumrad, I'm Robert Krulwich.
嘿, 我是Jad Abrumrad, 我是Robert Krulwich。
This is radiolab and today. well.
这是radiolab, 今天。 好吧。
Today, we're going to tell you a story which we hope does not become your future, but it raises a simple question.
今天, 我们要告诉你一个故事, 我们希望它不会成为你的未来, 但它提出了一个简单的问题。
We all have computers.
我们都有电脑。
We love computers.
我们热爱电脑。
We depend upon computers, but what if the cost of using your computer becomes more than you're willing to pay two stories today, which suggests that we might be at the very beginning of a nightmare.
我们依赖电脑, 但如果使用电脑的成本变得超过你今天愿意支付的两个故事, 这表明我们可能处于噩梦的最开始。
The first comes from a journalist, Inna Simone, and her mother Alina.
第一个故事来自一个记者, Inna Simone和她的母亲Alina。
I mean, do you want to start with my mom?
我的意思是, 你想从我妈妈开始吗？
Cause it really happened to her, you know, she only got in touch with me, maybe on day six. ..
因为它真的发生在她身上, 你知道, 她只与我联系, 也许在第六天。
Okay, so ...
好的, 所以...
Yeah, day 1 what happened was the first first thing that happened.
是的, 第1天发生的事情是第一件第一件发生的事情。
On day 1.
在第1天。
What happened that I called Tufts University IT services because my husband complaining that my computer is unbearably unbearably slow.
发生了什么, 我叫塔夫茨大学的IT服务, 因为我的丈夫抱怨说, 我的电脑是无法忍受的无法忍受的慢。
She tells IT I don't know what's going on every time I try and open a window, it's like click.
她告诉IT部门, 我不知道发生了什么, 每次我试图打开一个窗口, 它就像点击。
Pop click. practically stop to work in what do I do, they checked whatever, I said and probably nothing rebooted, so did nothing.
啪嗒一声。实际上是停止工作, 我做什么, 他们检查什么, 我说, 可能什么都没有重启, 所以什么都没做。
Basically, then, she went away for the weekend, and when I came back, I turned the computer on and like it was doing something, and I saw many, many windows covering a screen, and those windows multiplied.
基本上, 然后, 她去了周末, 当我回来的时候, 我打开电脑, 就像它在做什么, 我看到许多, 许多窗口覆盖了一个屏幕, 这些窗口倍增。
I cannot open any of them, and I could not figure ...
我无法打开它们中的任何一个, 而且我无法理解...
But it was very late at night, so she went bed.
但当时已经很晚了, 所以她上床了。
Got up the next day called Tufts again, asking for help
第二天起来又给塔夫茨打电话, 请求帮助
They had no idea what was going on.  - No
他们不知道发生了什么事。 - 没有
She says at this point, whatever the computer had been doing, it was done. All windows disappeared
她说, 在这一点上, 无论计算机一直在做什么, 它都已经完成。所有的窗口都消失了
Except now, anytime she tried to click.
除了现在, 只要她试图点击
Any of her files.
她的任何文件。
Pictures, videos I cannot open any of them. Instead, every time this message would pop up.
图片、视频, 我都无法打开它们。相反, 每次都会弹出这样的信息。
And the message says, what happened to your files.
消息说, 你的文件发生了什么。
All of your files have been protected with a strong encryption, encrypted using crypto wall.
你的所有文件都受到了强大的加密保护, 使用加密墙进行了加密。
This means that the structure and data within your file have been irrevocably (不可撤回地) changed.
这意味着你的文件中的结构和数据已经被不可撤回地改变。
And in order to
而为了
get them back to unlock files, you must pay five hundred US dollars if you really value your data,
为了让它们恢复到解锁文件, 如果你真的重视你的数据, 你必须支付500美元。
then we suggest that you do not waste valuable time searching for the solutions because they do not exist.
那么我们建议你不要浪费宝贵的时间去寻找解决方案, 因为他们不存在。
You're saying that somebody.
你是说, 有人。
Went into your computer and locked up all of your things, yeah.
进入你的电脑, 锁定了你所有的东西, 是的。
They gave me the exact count.
他们给了我确切的数字。
5726 files encrypted.
5726个文件被加密。
Wait, when you say they, did you have any image in your head of who's.
等等, 当你说他们的时候, 你的脑子里有没有谁的形象。
My first thought was Russia or Ukraine, which is even better. - Why? - Because you know everybody talks about excellent fantastic education there, especially math.
我的第一个想法是俄罗斯或乌克兰, 这甚至更好。- 因为你知道每个人都在谈论那里出色的梦幻般的教育, 尤其是数学。
I'm from there, I know.  - You know, she's right.
我来自那里, 我知道。 - 你知道, 她是对的。
They surpassed (胜过) the US and educating their kids when it comes to math and science, and they've got a severe underemployment (未就业) problem.
当涉及到数学和科学时, 他们在教育孩子方面超过了美国, 而且他们有一个严重的就业不足问题。
Especially outside of the major cities, which is where these viruses often trace down to not Moscow and Saint Petersburg, but we're talking about, you know, backwater.
特别是在大城市之外, 也就是这些病毒经常追踪到的地方, 不是莫斯科和圣彼得堡, 而是我们正在谈论的, 你知道, 落后的地方。
I was so positive that it comes from that part of the world that I wrote them in Russian.
我非常肯定地认为它来自世界的那个地方, 所以我用俄语写了它们。
[..] the criminal said, provided a link to a website where she could send them a message, you know. Customer support.
[......]罪犯说, 提供了一个网站的链接, 她可以给他们发信息, 你知道。客户支持。
I wrote them До все сдохли
我给他们写了 До все сдохли
I don't know how to translate it in English more accurately.
我不知道如何用英语更准确地翻译它。
Something like I wish you all die, but in Russian language, the word to die for humans or another word for animals.
类似于我希望你们都死, 但在俄语中, 死这个词是指人, 还是指另一个动物。
Use the animal one, of course, but you know they got the message.
当然是用动物的那个, 但你知道他们得到了这个信息。
Now Inna sais, she thought about just wiping the computer clean so that she wouldn't have to pay, but then it occurred to her that her husband had all these files on there, you know, like.
现在英娜说, 她想过把电脑擦干净, 这样她就不用付钱了, 但后来她想到, 她丈夫在那里有所有这些文件, 你知道, 比如。
Business receipts that he hadn't filed yet, but he's lazy to do so.
商业收据, 他还没有归档, 但他懒得这么做。
He has [..] and and she's right that like, you know, she has this tax information, and this reimbursement information, and ultimately.
他有[......], 而且她是对的, 比如, 你知道, 她有这些税务信息, 还有这些报销信息, 最终。
It's worth more than 500 dollars.
它的价值超过了500美元。
My husband did not want to pay, I overruled him.
我丈夫不想支付, 我否决了他。
So Inna decides to follow the instructions basically.
所以英娜决定基本上按照指示去做。
1. download and installed Tor browser, so.
1.下载并安装Tor浏览器, 所以。
She goes and installs this browser called Tor, which apparently.
她去安装了这个名为Tor的浏览器, 显然。
is not traceable 2. Run the browser and wait for initialization, she does that. 3. type in the address bar k pi 7YCR7jX Q
是无法追踪的 2. 运行浏览器, 等待初始化, 她这样做。3.在地址栏输入k pi 7YCR7jX Q
then she's directed to a site where basically tells her, look, if you don't trust us.
然后她被引导到一个网站, 那里基本上告诉她, 看, 如果你不相信我们。
We can decrypt one of your files for free as a sample that when you pay us.
我们可以免费解密你的一个文件, 作为一个样本, 当你付钱给我们。
You would know that you could really get all your files back, and I was curious.
你会知道, 你真的可以拿回你所有的文件, 我很好奇。
I decided that I will try.
我决定, 我将尝试。
So she clicked the button that said yes, and.
因此, 她点击了按钮, 说是的, 和。
I got one file back, but as soon as I did the clocks that taken, literally, she says, a little clock appeared at the top of the browser.
我得到了一个文件回来, 但只要我做的时钟, 采取, 从字面上看, 她说, 一个小时钟出现在浏览器的顶部。
They gave me exactly 7 days. 167 hours 59 minutes 59 seconds.
他们给了我正好7天。167小时59分钟59秒。
So you decrypt the thing and then suddenly it's a countdown.
所以你解密的东西, 然后突然它是一个倒计时。
Yes, they say.
是的, 他们说。
If you won't pay by this day.
如果你不在这一天前支付,
Then, the fine, will be doubled, and if you won't pay in one [..], then you will lose your files forever, and you'll never get it back.
那么, 罚款, 将增加一倍, 如果你不会支付在一个[... ...], 那么你将失去你的文件永远, 你永远不会得到它回来。
Now in the message, it had told you that she had to pay that 500 dollar fine, not in dollars, but in bitcoin.
在信息中, 它告诉你她必须支付500美元的罚款, 不是用美元, 而是用比特币。
You know, this was the first time in my life ever I heard the term bitcoins, so I uh found this website called coin cafe, where you can buy bitcoins and to buy this bitcoins is a nightmare.
你知道吗, 这是我人生中第一次听到比特币这个词, 所以我呃发现了一个叫硬币咖啡的网站, 在那里你可以买到比特币, 买这个比特币是一场噩梦。
It's a torture. What she needed to do was exchange 500 bucks for the requisite (必要的) amount of bitcoins, and at the time 500 bucks equal 1.37 bitcoins, but before she could make that exchange, she had to fill out all these forms of these questions.
这是一种折磨。她需要做的是用500块钱换取必要的比特币, 当时500块钱等于1.37个比特币, 但是在她进行兑换之前, 她必须填写所有这些表格和问题。
What happened?
发生了什么事？
What is the reason to buy bitcoin, and reasons were listed that one of them was ransom, so they knew that was.
购买比特币的原因是什么, 原因被列出, 其中一个是赎金, 所以他们知道那是。
Yes, it was the first reason to pay ransom to the criminals. Next, she says.
是的, 这是第一个向犯罪分子支付赎金的理由。接下来, 她说。
after you fill out all the forms, you have to make a picture and send them a photograph through the internet, OK? I did not have a camera. Because, she says her camera happened to be in the shop.
在你填完所有的表格后, 你必须做一张照片, 并通过互联网给他们发送照片, 好吗？我没有带相机。因为, 她说她的相机刚好在店里。
More than that, I have to make a picture of my husband holding a driver's license, send them this picture back.
不止如此, 我还得做一张我丈夫拿着驾照的照片, 把这张照片寄给他们。
It is the bank with the criminals? No, this is the people who sell you bitcoins in exchange for your money.
这是银行与罪犯的关系？不, 这是那些卖给你比特币来换取你钱的人。
I told you that it's a torture is unbelievable.
我告诉你, 这是一种折磨是不可思议的。
But eventually she was able to find a neighbor, borrow the camera, take the picture she needs to take.
但最终她还是找到了一个邻居, 借到了相机, 拍下了她需要的照片。
Then she had to get the money she wanted to exchange to coin cafe, and it turns out the preferred way to do it the most secure way to do it is not online, but through a money order.
然后她必须把她要兑换的钱拿到币吧, 结果发现首选的方式最安全的方式不是在网上, 而是通过汇票。
At least for the day right before the Thanksgiving, Wednesday. She still had about six days before the deadline, so she thought, all right.
至少在感恩节前的那一天, 即星期三。她在截止日期前还有大约六天时间, 所以她想, 好吧。
I'll just pop down to the post office, get a money order. But,
我就跑到邮局去, 拿一张汇票。但是。
Live from Boston.
来自波士顿的直播。
Lexington and the whole Massachusetts had a terrible, terrible snowstorm.  For a lot of us.
列克星敦和整个马萨诸塞州经历了一场可怕的、糟糕的暴风雪。 对于我们很多人来说。
This could be the biggest storm so far this winter. undrivable road. but I had to go to the post office.
这可能是今年冬天迄今为止最大的一场风暴。无法行驶的道路。但我必须去邮局。
So she ploughs (犁,奋力穿过) through the snow almost kills herself, but gets there, gets everything together, sends it off.
所以她犁雪, 几乎杀了自己, 但到了那里, 把所有东西放在一起, 送走了。
so finally, I send everything out.
所以最后, 我把所有东西都送出去了。
The post office assured me that they will get it on Friday, which is the first working day after that Thanksgiving. Okay.
邮局向我保证, 他们会在星期五收到, 那是感恩节后的第一个工作日。好的。
So on Friday, she called coin cafe,
所以在星期五, 她打电话给硬币咖啡馆。
they did not get it. On Saturday.
他们并没有收到。在星期六。
They did not get it. On Monday morning, nothing was delivered.
他们没有得到它。周一早上, 什么都没送来。
And I was desperate because my deadline was Tuesday, something
我很绝望, 因为我的最后期限是星期二, 大约12点。
like 12 o'clock, and I started calling the post office whatever nobody knows anything, they said yes two days, but there is no guarantee finally.
我开始给邮局打电话, 但没有人知道, 他们说是两天, 但最后也没有保证。
4 o'clock in the afternoon on Monday, but.
星期一下午4点, 但是。
24 hours before the deadline, they've got it.
在截止日期前24小时, 他们已经得到了它。
Yeah, and they send me bitcoins in exchange because they got my money, but.
是的, 他们给我发比特币作为交换, 因为他们得到了我的钱, 但是。
She says when she went online to check her bitcoin account.
她说当她上网查看她的比特币账户时,
I'm 13 dollars short.
我还差13美元。
Then basically, the exchange rate has changed on her.
然后基本上, 汇率在她身上发生了变化。
She bought it at 500, now it's 487
她在500买的, 现在是487了
How often do you change the exchange rate and they said every minute, but it's not a joke.
你多久改变一次汇率, 他们说每分钟, 但这不是一个笑话。
Yeah, every minute, I said, are you crazy, I was a double victim, I was victim square or victim cube, you see, because driving was terrible, I have to stand on my head to get a camera.
是的, 每分钟, 我说, 你疯了, 我是双重受害者, 我是受害者方块或受害者立方体, 你看, 因为驾驶很糟糕, 我必须站在我的头上去拿相机。
And then I was struggling to send them.
然后我还在挣扎着送他们。
That's the problem with this crime.
这就是这种犯罪的问题所在。
The criminals need a better way to get money from the victim.
犯罪分子需要一个更好的方法来从受害者那里得到钱。
But everything else is traceable.
但其他的东西都是可以追踪的。
I'm on the edge of my seat here.
我都快坐不住了。
So the you're 13 dollars short.
所以你还差13美元。
I am calling a day, they said, there is one more way, one more way, and what is it.
我叫了一天, 他们说, 还有一个办法, 还有一个办法, 那是什么。
We have an ATM machine.
我们有一台ATM机。
I said what, yeah, we have an ATM machine, only one and I said
我说什么, 是的, 我们有一个ATM机, 只有一个, 我说
Where is it, it's in Brooklyn. Brooklyn, New York?
它在哪里, 它在布鲁克林。布鲁克林, 纽约？
Yeah, oh.
是的, 哦。
Well, 200 miles away.
嗯, 200英里远。
Wait a second, I don't understand this.
等一下, 我不明白这个。
There was one ATM that is in the borough (区) of Brooklyn where you do not live. Exactly.
有一台ATM机是在你不住的布鲁克林区（区）的。正是如此。
But luckily, her daughter Alina lives in Brooklyn, you ask me how my daughter got involved, that's how. So she calls Alina, yeah.
但幸运的是, 她的女儿阿琳娜住在布鲁克林, 你问我的女儿是如何参与的, 就是这样。所以她给阿琳娜打电话, 是的。
My mom called me the night before the ransom was due.
我妈妈在赎金到期的前一天晚上给我打电话。
Are you aware of any of this at that point?
那时候你是否知道这些事情？
no, no.
不, 不。
I remember, you know, I was at night.
我记得, 你知道, 我是在晚上。
I had the TV on and I have a toddler.
我开着电视, 我有一个蹒跚学步的孩子。
You know, I always all these things going on.
你知道, 我总是所有这些事情都在进行。
I was probably on my laptop too.
我可能也在用我的笔记本电脑。
I was doing like 12 things, and my mom called, and she was like, upset with a capital U.
我正在做12件事情, 我妈妈打来电话, 她就像, 大写的不安。
She started ranting (咆哮) about criminals and ransom.
她开始咆哮（咆哮）关于罪犯和赎金。
And I literally thought she was like talking in air quotes.
我真的以为她是在用引号说话。
I'm like, oh, yeah, I know when I go to Texas and like, yeah, they're extortion (敲诈), and my mom was like, no, like, no, really a ransom.
我想, 哦, 是的, 我知道, 当我去德克萨斯州和喜欢, 是的, 他们是敲诈（敲诈）, 和我妈一样, 不, 像, 不, 真的是赎金。
They're really criminals, her mom told her Google crytowall, and I was like, holy shit this is really a thing, plus I started googling as she suggested I do
他们真的是罪犯, 她的妈妈告诉她谷歌crytowall, 我很喜欢, 神圣的狗屎, 这是真的一个东西, 再加上我开始谷歌, 因为她建议我做的
and found out the police departments had paid this, that sheriff's department in Dickson, Tennessee, has just paid it to unlock like you know, 70 plus thousand case files, and I was like, yeah.
发现警察部门已经支付了这个, 田纳西州迪克森的警长部门, 刚刚支付了它, 以解锁像你知道的, 70多万个案件文件, 我当时想, 是的。
Hold, so these crooks go after police department.  They've got after governments, universities, corporations, police departments and did a question ever why my mom. - no, not at all, because like a million people in the US have been infected with this very thing.
等等, 所以这些骗子去找警察部门。 他们已经得到了政府, 大学, 公司, 警察部门后, 做了一个问题曾经为什么我的妈妈。- 没有, 完全没有, 因为在美国有一百万人被感染了这种东西。
Yes, anyhow, next day, less than six hours left. Inna says to Alina
是的, 无论如何, 第二天, 剩下不到六个小时。英娜对阿琳娜说
Please go to this ATM so we can just be done with this whole thing.
请到这个自动取款机那里去, 这样我们就可以结束这整件事情了。
You can got it later, but I can tell you that in the morning, she said, I have a date for my granddaughter date to play that I won't be able to do it until 12 o'clock, and they called again, I said.
你可以稍后得到它, 但我可以告诉你, 在早上, 她说, 我有一个约会, 我的孙女约会玩, 我将无法做到这一点, 直到12点钟, 他们再次打电话, 我说。
I am crazy.
我真是疯了。
I don't have time, so I go out to green point, this ATM, and you know.
我没有时间, 所以我出去到绿色点, 这个ATM机, 你知道。
I just want to add that what do you had your play date. you didn't I called you.
我只是想补充说, 你有什么你的游戏日期。你没有我叫你。
Fortunately, you make it right, okay, so I cut my play date short. sorry, forget that crucial detail.
幸运的是, 你做得对, 好吧, 所以我缩短了我的游戏日期。 对不起, 忘记了这个关键的细节。
And I go out to green point, and they have an ATM and,
然后我就去了绿点, 他们有一台自动取款机和。
I'm just worried that there's going to be 57 people, all lined up at the single ATM, but you're there were.
我只是担心会有57个人, 都在单一的自动取款机前排队, 但你在那里是。
Totally not 57 people.
完全没有57个人。
I mean, most people do take care of this um remotely like there was no one at this ATM.
我的意思是, 大多数人确实照顾到了这个嗯远程像这个自动取款机上没有人。
But what's funny about the ATM is like i'm expecting, like.
但是, 关于自动取款机的有趣之处在于, 就像我期待的那样。
Yeah, i've been to an ATM a capital one account.
是的, 我去过自动取款机一个资本一帐户。
I know what an ATM is, you know, but this is on the second floor of a workshare space in Brooklyn.
我知道自动取款机是什么, 你知道, 但这是在布鲁克林的一个工作共享空间的二楼。
It was like, in the hallway, there was like a bike hanging from a wall kind of blocking in.
这就像, 在走廊里, 有一个自行车挂在墙上, 有点像挡住了。
There was like a paper sign taped to the wall that just had a print out from a computer that just said Bitcoin ATM, all lower case letters in an arrow to this phone booth.
墙上贴着一个纸牌, 上面写着从电脑上打印出来的比特币提款机, 所有的小写字母都是一个箭头, 指向这个电话亭。
It looked very Soviet like if you've seen photos of those phones with no botnets.
它看起来非常像苏联人, 如果你看过那些没有僵尸网络的电话的照片。
The receiver and it's totally scary, it's like red line?
接收器和它是完全可怕的, 它是像红线？
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
是啊, 是啊, 是啊。
You just pick it up and like somebody's always on the other line or something.
你只是拿起它, 像有人总是在另一条线上或东西。
It was like that it was just this box with a screen and no botnets and a camera eye.
它是这样的, 它只是这个盒子, 有一个屏幕, 没有僵尸网络和一个摄像头的眼睛。
And what you do is you hold up your QVC code, is that what they're called QVC?
你要做的就是举起你的QVC代码, 就是他们所说的QVC吗？
What are they QRC, the barcode? Yeah, yeah, it's like a barcode.
他们是什么QRC, 条形码？是的, 是的, 这就像一个条形码。
And my mom had emailed it to me and was like.
和我的妈妈有电子邮件它给我, 是这样的：
You need to print this out, and this is essentially gives you access to my account to top it off, you know, and so I put this QRC code up to the camera eye, and it kind of, [blup], and then it was like we are accessing your account.
你需要打印出来, 这是本质上给你访问我的帐户, 以拓宽它, 你知道, 所以我把这个QRC代码到相机的眼睛, 它种, [blup], 然后它是像我们正在访问您的帐户。
I got a spinny wheel.
我有一个旋转的轮子。
You've got the wheel of death, no... spinning wheel, Alina starts frantically (发狂似的) dialing her mom, the guys at Coin Cafe.
你有死亡之轮, 不......旋转的轮子, 阿琳娜开始疯狂地（发狂似的）拨打她妈妈的电话, 硬币咖啡馆的人。
I called, you know, I left like three phone messages and I left far, so finally, they called me back like 20 minutes later.
我打了电话, 你知道, 我留了三条电话留言, 我留得很远, 所以最后, 他们在20分钟后给我回电话。
Said, okay, we're sending a technician over to fix the machine.
他们说, 好的, 我们会派一个技术员过来修理机器。
Which was very cool.
这非常酷。
I didn't think that would happen, and so you know, the technician was there, and he.
我没想到会发生这种情况, 所以你知道, 技术员在那里, 他。
Fixed the machine.
修复了机器。
And he helped me deposit these 25 dollars.
他还帮我存入这25美元。
And then he was talking and he was he was like, yeah, you know, he knew my mom, because you know, he'd been talking to her on the phone. He's like, I feel so bad for your mom.
然后他在说话, 他是他就像, 是的, 你知道, 他认识我妈妈, 因为你知道, 他一直在和她通电话。他就说, 我为你妈妈感到很难过。
We've been getting so many of these cases, and i'm like, why are you why are. - a lot of these cases?
我们已经得到了这么多这样的案件, 我想, 为什么你为什么。- 很多这样的案件？
Yeah, I was like, why are you guys getting so?
是的, 我当时想, 为什么你们会得到这么？
Why is everyone coming to you, and he's like, oh, I know why.
为什么每个人都来找你们, 他就说, 哦, 我知道原因。
Because in the ransom note that they give a list of preferred vendors and we are number one, or two.
因为在赎金条上, 他们给出了一个首选供应商的名单, 而我们是第一, 或者第二。
introduction what a bad introduction to bitcoin like we're going to hold you ransom for all your information until you, you know, use this new currency to pay us off, I mean, that's so terrible.
对比特币的介绍真不怎么样, 就像我们要用你的所有信息来勒索你的赎金, 直到你, 你知道, 用这种新货币来支付我们, 我是说, 这太可怕了。
This is Mike and John .
这是麦克和约翰.
They are the co-owners of coin cafe.
他们是硬币咖啡馆的共同拥有者。
I had a few weeks back, a grandmother who was in tears. She was going to lose all of her family photos, and because the deadline was coming up, you know.
几周前, 我有一个老奶奶, 她哭了。她要失去她所有的家庭照片, 而且因为最后期限快到了, 你知道。
Crying on the phone to me and god it, it felt horrible
在电话里跟我哭诉, 天啊, 感觉太可怕了
Now clearly, people who sell bitcoin just believe that there should be a digital currency that is decentralized, that doesn't rely on the banks, but unfortunately, it has become the currency of choice for ransom, and so, they're in this weird position. so,
现在很明显, 卖比特币的人只是相信应该有一种去中心化的数字货币, 不依赖银行, 但不幸的是, 它已经成为赎金的首选货币, 所以, 他们处于这个奇怪的位置。 所以。
It's a tricky thing, because like I can't sell bitcoin to someone who,
这是个很棘手的问题, 因为我不能把比特币卖给一个,
I know is going to do something illegal with it, right?
我知道会用它做一些违法的事情, 对吧？
That's Will Wheeler, who runs a bitcoin exchange called express coin, and he says he and other exchanges are really worried right now that if they keep helping the little guys pay the ransom in order to get their files back, they are, in effect, making themselves accessories to a crime.
这就是威尔-惠勒, 他经营着一家名为 "快递币 "的比特币交易所, 他说他和其他交易所现在真的很担心, 如果他们继续帮助那些小家伙支付赎金以取回他们的文件, 他们实际上是在让自己成为犯罪的帮凶。
I finally got a call back from Vincent,
我终于接到了文森特的回电。
which is the federal authority for a financial crime enforcement network.
这是一个金融犯罪执法网络的联邦当局。
They said that we could perceive paying a ransom, unlawful activity.
他们说, 我们可以认为支付赎金是非法的活动。
And so they might choose to use that against the company.
因此, 他们可能会选择利用这一点来对付该公司。
Who helps out right and likely until we get a straight answer from Vincent, we'll take the overly cautious approach and start declining these transactions, even though in your heart, you want to help.
谁来帮忙是对的, 在我们从文森特那里得到一个直接的答案之前, 我们会采取过于谨慎的做法, 开始拒绝这些交易, 即使在你的心里, 你想帮忙。
I mean, do I want to risk being indicted for helping you get your travel receipts reimbursed from your company.
我的意思是, 我是否想冒着被起诉的风险, 帮助你从你的公司获得旅行收据的报销。
And I mean, to me, the answer is no.
而我的意思是, 对我来说, 答案是否定的。
In any case.
在任何情况下。
After Alina deposits the extra 25 bucks in her mom's bitcoin account, Inna the mom goes online.
Alina把多余的25块钱存入她妈妈的比特币账户后, 妈妈Inna上网了。
Then I clicked and it was gone.
然后我点击了一下, 它就不见了。
But then about an hour later, I went to my computer and there was another message that "you are late".
但大约一个小时后, 我去了我的电脑, 又有一条消息说 "你迟到了"。
It turns out that I was two and a half hours late.
事实证明, 我迟到了两个半小时。
You have to pay 1300 dollars roughly, I did not have anybody to turn to.
你必须支付1300美元左右, 我没有任何人可以求助。
So she went to that same website where you can write them a message.
所以她去了那个同样的网站, 在那里你可以给他们写一个消息。
I wrote them that I was late, but I mentioned the snowstorm, the things given, which they probably will not bear off.
我给他们写了我迟到了, 但我提到了暴风雪, 给的东西, 他们可能不会承担。
And of course, the the wonderful US mail service, I said that I tried and I was only two hours late. And then all of a sudden, I am getting a message you paid in full without any explanation, nothing. You paid.
当然, 奇妙的美国邮件服务, 我说我试过了, 我只迟到了两个小时。然后突然间, 我收到一条信息, 你全额支付, 没有任何解释, 什么都没有。你支付了。
That's it, and I got all my files back.
就这样, 我拿回了我所有的文件。
Do you think that they took pity on her?
你认为他们怜悯她吗？
maybe. I felt that it's over.
也许吧。我觉得一切都结束了。
Finally, it's really over.
最后, 它真的结束了。
It does make you wonder who these people are there?
这确实让你怀疑这些人是谁？
We've a story about that up next.
我们有一个关于这个的故事了。
Hey, I'm Jad Abrumrad. I'm Robert Krulwich.
嘿, 我是贾德Abrumrad。我是Robert Krulwich。
This is radiolab, so here's the next obvious question, who did this to Inna? Do we know anything about them?
这是radiolab, 所以这里是下一个明显的问题, 谁做了这个英娜？我们对他们有了解吗？
But we put that question to Joseph Menn, investigate reporter for Reuters, done ton of work in this area, and his hunch (直觉) was that Inna is right. We're talking people Russian speaking folks by and large.
但我们把这个问题交给了约瑟夫-门恩, 他是路透社的调查记者, 在这个领域做了大量工作, 他的预感是英娜是对的。我们说的是讲俄语的人, 而且是大体上讲俄语的人。
Do you have a book called fatal system error, which is sort of a deep dive into the Russian hacking scene and much of it as you would expect.
你是否有一本名为《致命的系统错误》的书, 这本书对俄罗斯黑客活动进行了深入研究, 其中大部分内容正如你所期望的。
You know, young guys, early 20s
你知道, 年轻的家伙, 20岁出头
Of grubby, by and large, they do not live a lavish (大方的) lifestyle.
邋遢的人, 总的来说, 他们并没有过着奢侈的生活。
There are guys at the top of these criminal organizations that are very flashy. And they're sort of pop icon, some of them in the same way that rap stars are in the US there's a hacker magazine, which you know as guys with their sports cars and the supermodels and whatever, you know, buying bottle service at you know.
在这些犯罪组织的顶层, 有一些人是非常华丽的。他们是流行偶像, 其中一些人就像说唱明星一样, 在美国有一本黑客杂志, 你知道这些人有跑车和超级名模之类的东西, 你知道, 在你知道的情况下买酒服务。
Discos between the morning.
上午之间的迪斯科舞厅。
Those are the guys who hire the twenty year olds.
这些人就是雇用20岁的人。
They hire the twenty year old or their franchises, and he says the twenty year old grants work at office Parks yeah.
他们雇用二十岁的人或他们的特许经营权, 他说二十岁的人在帕克斯办公室工作, 是的。
And it's like a call center type of atmosphere. so is there like, you know.
而且它就像一个呼叫中心类型的氛围。所以是否有像, 你知道。
That's producer Kelsey Patrick. I went in a cubicle, at his computer board, he has a meeting later with Judy in HR, and he's mad about it.
那是制片人凯尔西-帕特里克。我进了一个隔间, 在他的电脑板上, 他稍后与人力资源部的朱迪开会, 他对此很生气。
Is that the kind of like environment that these people are in? For the most part,
这就是这些人所处的那种喜欢的环境吗？在大多数情况下。
So yes. the larger point is that it's not just like your lone wolf, pimply faced hacker anymore.
所以是的。更重要的一点是, 它不只是像你的独狼, 长着疙瘩的黑客了。
Cybercrime is now super organized.
网络犯罪现在是超级有组织的。
It is often corporate.
它通常是企业。
It is big business and the whole sort of economy seems to revolve around these secret sites where people come together to buy and sell things like that
它是大企业, 整个经济似乎围绕着这些秘密网站, 人们在那里聚集在一起, 购买和出售这样的东西。
Ransomeware from our last story.
我们上一个故事中的勒索软件。
There are these underground web forums, and there's a variety, some are available.
有这些地下网络论坛, 而且有各种各样的, 有些是可以用的。
You can reach you on the open internet.
你可以在开放的互联网上找到你。
The more impressive ones are password protected, you know, you have to know somebody to get in the really, really fancy ones.
更令人印象深刻的是有密码保护的, 你知道, 你必须认识一些人, 才能进入真正的、真正花哨的论坛。
You have to have a couple of people vouch for you.
你必须有几个人为你担保。
You actually have to apply with your resume.
你实际上必须用你的简历来申请。
Your hackers resume.
你的黑客简历。
Here are the things I can bring.
以下是我可以带来的东西。
These are the kinds of hacking exploits that i've had, and therefore I should be part of your exclusive club.
这些是我曾经有过的各种黑客漏洞, 因此我应该成为你的独家俱乐部的一部分。
That's Dina Temple-Raston, an NPR
这是Dina Temple-Raston, NPR的网络犯罪记者。
cyber crime correspondent. She's been tracking the government's attempts to shut down some of these sites, which she describes as sort of a hackers black market bazaar.
网络犯罪记者。她一直在跟踪政府关闭这些网站的尝试, 她把这些网站描述为黑客黑市集市的一种。
So let's say someone is looking for a bunch of credit card numbers that have been stolen, you can get it there. There's one price if they're mastercard gold and another price for you know, a higher level credit, whatever. Let's say.
因此, 假设有人正在寻找一堆被盗的信用卡号码, 你可以在那里得到它。如果他们是万事达卡金卡, 有一个价格, 而另一个价格是你知道的, 一个更高级别的信用, 不管是什么。比方说。
You wanted to know about a boss or an employee or a girlfriend. You can get this piece of software that allows you to turn on their phone
你想知道一个老板或一个雇员或一个女朋友。你可以得到这块软件, 让你打开他们的手机
at any time. You could basically eavesdrop (窃听) on them because you're in the pocket.
在任何时候。你基本上可以偷听（窃听）他们, 因为你就在他们的口袋里。
And for 300 dollars a month, you would actually get customer service. And the prices actually keep coming down.
每个月花300美元, 你就能真正得到客户服务。而且价格实际上不断下降。
It's a very, very evolved fluid marketplace.
这是一个非常, 非常进化的流动市场。
There's feedback and there's escrow (第三方保管).
有反馈, 有托管（第三方保管）。
There are feedback forums.
有反馈论坛。
That thief was not really there was like didn't didn't do the thief.
那个小偷并不是真的存在, 就像没有没有做小偷。
The robbery right? Absolutely. Particularly for something you'll see it a lot for freshness of credit cards because you know it's easy to say, you know, here are 10000 credit card numbers, but if they're credit card numbers, they've been out for a while and get declined, everybody, you've just wasted your money.
抢劫吧？绝对的。特别是对于一些你会看到它很多的信用卡的新鲜度, 因为你知道这很容易说, 你知道, 这里有10000个信用卡号码, 但如果他们的信用卡号码, 他们已经出了一段时间, 得到拒绝, 大家, 你只是浪费了你的钱。
And these people are called as rippers, and they're ripping you off. And they will get banned from the forum. Wow, so it's reputational, just like everywhere else.
这些人被称为骗子, 他们在骗你的钱。而且他们会被禁止进入论坛。哇, 所以这是声誉问题, 就像其他地方一样。
Yeah, and it's it's as good as Ebay.
是的, 而且它和Ebay一样好。
If you feel safe doing business on Ebay, there's no reason you shouldn't feel safe doing business with the criminals.
如果你觉得在Ebay上做生意是安全的, 你就没有理由不觉得与罪犯做生意是安全的。
Now all of this to me frankly felt like just sexy hacker talk until a couple of months ago.
现在, 所有这些对我来说坦率地说, 感觉只是性感的黑客谈话, 直到几个月前。
Dina started telling us about this one particular site, actually the biggest of these kinds of sites that's out there.
迪娜开始告诉我们关于这个特别的网站, 实际上是这些网站中最大的一个。
It's called Darkode.
它叫Darkode。
Yeah, the way it has been described by law enforcement is sort of an Amazon.com
是的, 它已经被执法部门描述为有点像亚马逊网站
for hackers. Actually here, specifically how US attorney David Higgson described to her in an interview, Darkode
为黑客。事实上, 在这里, 特别是美国律师大卫-希格森在采访中向她描述, Darkode
is the largest English speaking criminal cyber crime forum in the world.
是世界上最大的讲英语的网络犯罪论坛。
And, I think most people know silk road, and they know, for example, you could get a contract hit from silk road and drugs and guns and everything else, so would it be right for me to say that this was sort of a silk road for hackers?
而且, 我想大多数人都知道丝绸之路, 他们知道, 例如, 你可以从丝绸之路上获得合同的打击, 毒品和枪支和其他一切, 所以我说这是一种黑客的丝绸之路, 这是否正确？
Yeah, I wouldn't want to draw that direct comparison.
是的, 我不想做这种直接比较。
I think it's probably accurate.
我认为这可能是准确的。
I would say that all measure of cybercrime you see and watch around the world was in some form of fashion connected to it.
我想说的是, 你在世界各地看到的所有网络犯罪的措施都是以某种形式与之相关的。
So we got really interested in this world of this site.
因此, 我们得到了真正的兴趣在这个世界上的这个网站。
Darkode and the people in it, and so with Dina,
Darkode和里面的人, 所以与Dina。
We started calling around trying to find anyone that would talk.
我们开始四处打电话, 试图找到任何愿意交谈的人。
And after weeks of searching and calling and lawyering, we found a guy who agreed to go in the record. My name is Daniel Placik.
经过几周的搜索、打电话和请律师, 我们找到了一个同意记录的人。我的名字是丹尼尔-普拉西克。
And I am a reformed hacker.
我是一个改过自新的黑客。
As far as we know, Dan has never talked about this, publicly. So how did you get involved with Darkode? Well,
据我们所知, 丹从未公开谈论过此事。那么, 你是如何参与Darkode的？嗯。
I was one of the people who created it, a very long time ago.
我是创建它的人之一, 在很久以前。
Daniel's story begins not in Russia, but in Milwaukee.
丹尼尔的故事不是从俄罗斯开始的, 而是在密尔沃基。
Sure.
当然。
Well, let me let me start with a little bit of a ...
好吧, 让我让我先说一点......。
small middle class suburb right outside Milwaukee.
小的中产阶级郊区, 就在密尔沃基外面。
You have brothers and sisters? Two younger brothers and two younger sisters,
你有兄弟姐妹吗？两个弟弟和两个妹妹。
Big family. Did you have to share rooms with them or in your own little Kingdom. I shared a room with both my brothers for a lot of years.
大家庭。你是和他们共用一个房间还是在你自己的小王国里。我和我的两个哥哥共用一个房间, 有很多年了。
In fact, that sort of plays into the story because he says what he would do to sort of escape, he's go to the basement and play video games.
事实上, 这也是故事的一部分, 因为他说他会做什么来逃避, 他会去地下室玩电子游戏。
So, yes, the stereotypical hacker in his parents' basement.
所以, 是的, 刻板的黑客在他父母的地下室。
It's quite hilarious.
这是相当搞笑的。
Dan says his hacking began innocently enough when he would monkey with games like Age of Empires.
丹说, 他的黑客行为开始时是很无辜的, 他对《帝国时代》等游戏进行捣乱。
I changed the graphics, changed the artificial intelligence in the game,
我改变了图形, 改变了游戏中的人工智能。
the way it plays, rework it, create new maps, that type of thing um, something I enjoyed. And slowly throughout my teenage years that developed into something more,
我改变了图形, 改变了游戏中的人工智能, 改变了它的玩法, 重新设计它, 创造新的地图, 这些都是我喜欢的东西。在我十几岁的时候, 慢慢地发展成更多的东西。
I did not get along well with a lot of my peers in in great middle schools.
在伟大的中学里, 我和很多同龄人相处得并不融洽。
So I spent um a lot more time on the computer and on myself than I did socially, at least at that age. And he says one day he was in,
所以我花了很多时间在电脑和自己身上, 而不是在社会上, 至少在那个年龄段。他说有一天他在。
A chat room and an Internet chat room was called game search, talking with a bunch of other people loved video games. And at some point along the way, he meets this guy.
一个聊天室, 一个互联网聊天室被称为游戏搜索, 与其他一堆人交谈, 喜欢视频游戏。而在这一过程中的某个时刻, 他遇到了这个家伙。
You know, this particular guy was into, you know, botnets.
你知道, 这个特别的家伙是成, 你知道, 僵尸网络。
Oh, yes, botnets, we all cry, just remind us, what's what's going on there? Botnets are you know, malware viruses installed on computers.
哦, 是的, 僵尸网络, 我们都哭了, 只是提醒我们, 什么是怎么回事呢？僵尸网络是你知道的, 安装在电脑上的恶意软件病毒。
And, botnets are the way to centrally control a whole lot of affected computers. Just to put this in context for saying, I think this is totally fascinating, Joseph Menn says this whole botnet situation started with spam.
而且, 僵尸网络是集中控制一大批受影响的计算机的方式。只是为了把这个背景说出来, 我认为这是完全迷人的, 约瑟夫-门恩说这整个僵尸网络的情况始于垃圾邮件。
One of the easiest ways to make money on the internet back to 2000 was spam. Spam is, in an opinion extensions, and i'm in Nairobi.
早在2000年, 互联网上最容易赚钱的方法之一就是垃圾邮件。垃圾邮件是, 在一个意见扩展, 我在内罗毕。
What happened was that in the olden days, most servers, mail servers, acted as open relays.
发生的事情是, 在过去的日子里, 大多数服务器, 邮件服务器, 作为开放的继电器。
Meaning the mail people wouldn't really pay attention to who was sending, so the spammers with.
意思是说, 人们不会真正注意到谁在发送, 所以垃圾邮件发送者。
Spam with abandon. And then spammers got to be enough of a problem that the techies of the world decided that's it.
垃圾邮件被抛弃了。然后, 垃圾邮件发送者成为一个足够的问题, 世界上的技术人员决定, 这是它。
They started to block people like if they found a guy who they thought was sending too many product emails or whatever, they would block his IP address so that he couldn't send any more mail.
他们开始阻止人们, 比如他们发现一个人, 他们认为他发送了太多的产品邮件或其他东西, 他们会阻止他的IP地址, 这样他就不能再发送任何邮件。
So what the spammers and their contractors then needed to do was to have a bunch of clean IP addresses and send spam.
因此, 垃圾邮件发送者和他们的承包商需要做的是拥有一堆干净的IP地址并发送垃圾邮件。
From that, so what they did, which is totally genius, totally evil, is they hired a bunch of programmers to create a bunch of viruses, disseminated (传播) those viruses across the internet.
因此, 他们所做的, 完全是天才的, 完全是邪恶的, 是他们雇用了一群程序员来创造一堆病毒, 在互联网上传播这些病毒。
Accidentally click or open something to get them onto their computer.
不小心点击或打开一些东西, 让他们进入自己的电脑。
And then suddenly the spammers could now remote control our computers at a distance, whatever they wanted for maybe just an hour or two a night to send out their spam because these were clean IP addresses.
然后突然间, 垃圾邮件发送者现在可以远程控制我们的电脑, 不管他们想做什么, 也许只是每晚一两个小时来发送他们的垃圾邮件, 因为这些是干净的IP地址。
Of course, what happened is that once the spammers had these botnets, they started thinking, hey, I could do something else with this, and the next thing that came along was denial of service attacks.
当然, 发生的事情是, 一旦垃圾邮件发送者拥有这些僵尸网络, 他们开始思考, 嘿, 我可以用这个做别的事情, 接下来出现的事情是拒绝服务攻击。
You can have all of them try to contact Ebay.com at the same time, and knock over Ebay. This first gentleman that I ran into, so he had a botnet of well over 1000 computers, which you know at the time was amazing to me.
你可以让所有的人同时尝试联系Ebay.com, 并打翻Ebay。我遇到的第一位先生, 所以他有一个超过1000台电脑的僵尸网络, 你知道在当时对我来说是惊人的。
You know, by today's standards of thousands for a botnet, that is, is nothing.
你知道, 以今天的标准, 一个僵尸网络有几千台, 那是, 什么都不是。
Now they can get up into the millions.
现在他们可以达到数百万台。
But um, you know, back then, it was quite incredible to me. And because he says he was in this chat room, this guy was there and this guy would get into fights with people. And any time he did, he'd point his 1000 computer drone army at that enemy.
但是, 嗯, 你知道, 在当时, 这对我来说是相当不可思议的。因为他说他在这个聊天室里, 这个家伙在那里, 这个家伙会和人打架。而任何时候, 他都会把他的1000台电脑无人机军队对准那个敌人。
And the few men, I'm going to knock your internet offline.
而那几个人, 我要把你的网络打掉。
And there's nothing you can do about it.
而你对此无能为力。
For what was something in a game, he could knock the game server that they were playing on offline,
对于游戏中的东西, 他可以把他们正在玩的游戏服务器打掉。
You know, stop their game.
你知道, 停止他们的游戏。
Things like that.
像这样的事情。
It's like you can take away his ball back in, 1935. That is exactly it, taking away someone else's ball over the Internet, this for some reason, intrigued you.
这就像你可以拿走他的球回来, 1935年。这正是它, 在互联网上夺走别人的球, 这出于某种原因, 让你很感兴趣。
Yes, was amazing to me.
是的, 对我来说很神奇。
I'm like you have control of 1000 computers.
我就像你控制了1000台电脑。
Wow, you know how how did you do this. At the time, I had never heard of botnets.
哇, 你知道你是如何做到这一点的。当时, 我从未听说过僵尸网络。
I didn't know about any of this stuff, like how did you, how did you get the software to do this? how did you get it onto all these computers. And he was quite happy to tell you all that? Oh, he certainly was particular gentleman, had a very large ego.
我不知道这些东西, 比如你是怎么做到的, 你是怎么得到这个软件的, 你是怎么把它放到所有这些电脑上的。他很乐意告诉你这一切？哦, 他肯定是特别的绅士, 有一个非常大的自我。
And did you see him as a bad guy?
你认为他是个坏人吗？
Yeah, to be honest, I think at that age, I didn't really think about it that deeply.
是的, 说实话, 我认为在那个年龄段, 我并没有真正深入思考这个问题。
It's the internet.
这是互联网。
It's it's a lot harder to do.
这是一个很难做到的。
Um kind of quantify right and wrong there.
嗯一种量化的权利和错误。
I mean, now, it's easy to look back at that and say, yeah.
我的意思是, 现在, 这很容易回头看, 说, 是的。
This is wrong, but it's not like going up to someone and punching them in the face.
这是不对的, 但它不像走到别人面前, 打他们的脸。
There's no human connection there.
那里没有人际关系。
You don't see these people or feel these people.
你看不到这些人, 也感觉不到这些人。
He says at the time, it was just sheer (十足) curiosity. So he says he asked this pied piper guy to send him some of the bot software that made the botnet go. And,
他说, 当时, 这只是纯粹的（十足）好奇。所以他说, 他要求这个吹笛人给他发送一些僵尸软件, 使僵尸网络的发展。而且。
that really intrigued me, you know, digging through the source code,
这真的让我很感兴趣, 你知道, 通过源代码的挖掘。
trying to understand what is this thing doing, how does it work, how does it tick? This guy, was he a good coder? Like, was he good at it?
试图了解这个东西在做什么, 它是如何工作的, 它是如何运作的？这个人, 他是一个好的编码员吗？比如, 他擅长这个吗？
No, no, I would, you know, in hindsight (事后聪明) now he's what I would classify as a script kiddie, you know someone script kiddie.
不, 不, 我会, 你知道, 在事后聪明）现在他是什么, 我会归类为一个脚本的孩子, 你知道有人脚本的孩子。
So a script kiddie is is someone who has just enough technical ability to uh.
因此, 一个脚本kiddie是一个人谁拥有足够的技术能力, 呃。
Huh, kind of take some tools and software that other people have created and just use them.
嗯, 那种采取一些工具和软件, 其他人已经创建, 只是使用它们。
Now to fast forward. As Dan went the opposite direction of the script kiddies and got better and better and started making these botnets that could literally spy on people as they were using their computers. Interesting to see all the porn that people were watching, that type of thing.
现在要快进了。由于丹走的是与脚本小子相反的方向, 并且变得越来越好, 开始制作这些僵尸网络, 可以从字面上监视人们使用他们的计算机。有意思的是, 看到人们正在观看的所有色情内容, 这种类型的东西。
He says he found himself in another chat room, that was called bot talk.
他说, 他发现自己在另一个聊天室, 这被称为机器人谈话。
It's kind of a place where hackers swap tips, brag like, hey, look what I did.
这是一种地方, 黑客交换技巧, 吹嘘像, 嘿, 看我做了什么。
I deface this website, take a look, and he says one day he was talking with a coder friend of his guy named Izelda.
他说, 有一天, 他和他的一个名叫Izelda的编码员朋友聊天。
Why don't we set up a community where we can really filter who gets to join and don't let all these script kiddies and idiots in, I actually chose the name.
我们为什么不建立一个社区, 在那里我们可以真正过滤谁可以加入, 不要让所有这些脚本儿童和白痴加入, 实际上是我选择了这个名字。
I came up with that nice, lame name.
我想出了这个好听又蹩脚的名字。
I actually think it's pretty good.
我实际上认为这很好。
What's the name again, Darkode, Darkode, I think, right.
名字是什么来着, Darkode, Darkode, 我想, 对。
It seemed cooler with the K O D E
有了K O D E, 它看起来更酷了。
Yeah.
是的。
So we chose the name and started getting the site set up.
所以我们选择了这个名字并开始建立网站。
The rules where it would be invited only so you had to, and each new person would be required to demonstrate their skill.
它的规则是只接受邀请, 所以你必须, 而且每个新来的人都需要展示他们的技能。
You know, here's a piece of software that I created, or here's a video of my botnet in action.
你知道, 这是我创造的一个软件, 或者这是我的僵尸网络行动的视频。
And at some point, I'm not too long after was created.
而在某种程度上, 我在不久后被创建。
It was decided for one reason or another that, you know, we got all these programmers on here.
由于这样或那样的原因决定, 你知道, 我们在这里得到了所有这些程序员。
That's great, but you know, they also want to be able to sell some of the stuff they're making.
这是伟大的, 但你知道, 他们也希望能够出售一些他们所做的东西。
So let's invite some people who would be willing to buy some of this stuff.
因此, 让我们邀请一些愿意购买这些东西的人。
This now begins to sound like a fair.
这现在听起来像一个展览会。
You say I have a burglars tool.
你说我有一个窃贼的工具。
Do you have a door, you want a burgle and then you have I'll rent you, my tool.
你是否有一扇门, 你想入室盗窃, 然后你有我租给你, 我的工具。
That's a simplification.
这是一个简化的说法。
But yeah, people would post and say, I'm looking to buy X or here's this piece of software I created, here's all the things it does.
但是, 是的, 人们会发帖说, 我想买X, 或者这是我创造的这块软件, 这是它的所有功能。
Here's some screenshots of it in action, and here's the price could be a certain type of botnet software.
这是它的一些行动截图, 这里的价格可能是某种类型的僵尸网络软件。
It could be buying a botnet that itself.
它可能是购买一个僵尸网络, 本身。
You know if you don't want to build one yourself, you want to buy one that somebody else already created and has going.
你知道, 如果你不想自己建立一个, 你想买一个别人已经创建并正在进行的。
I mean, I can get you onto 200 or 20000 computers.
我的意思是, 我可以让你进入200或20000台电脑。
Just give me a check.
只要给我一张支票。
Yeah, what they called them were installs.
是的, 他们所说的是安装。
Installs, you know. Hey guys, I've got installs and they're 10 dollars per 1000, something like that.
安装, 你知道。嘿, 伙计们, 我有安装, 他们是每1000个10美元, 类似的东西。
This is something that is sort of surprising to us that when it comes to botnets that there's this whole rental market that's frighteningly affordable, it's bargain basement.
这是一种让我们感到惊讶的东西, 当涉及到僵尸网络时, 有这样一个完整的租赁市场, 它是可怕的实惠, 它是便宜的。
In fact, we were talking with one reporter, Kelly Jackson Higgins.
事实上, 我们正在与一位记者凯利-杰克逊-希金斯交谈。
who's the executive editor of darkreading.com, which is a cyber security news site.
他是darkreading.com的执行编辑, 这是一个网络安全新闻网站。
And she told us, you know, you can actually rent a botnet if you really wanted to, you could rent a botnet for one hour for about 38 dollars a month.
她告诉我们, 你知道, 你实际上可以租一个僵尸网络, 如果你真的想, 你可以租一个僵尸网络一个小时, 每月约38美元。
In some cases, as low as 20 dollars a month
在某些情况下, 低至每月20美元。
I could rent a botnet for 20 bucks a month? You could. It's like renting space.
我可以用20块钱一个月租一个僵尸网络？你可以。这就像租借空间。
You wanna use this to go do damage somewhere or you want to make a statement or you have some plan for it or you want to send some spam here you go, you could go online right now.
你想用这个去破坏某个地方, 或者你想发表一个声明, 或者你有一些计划, 或者你想发送一些垃圾邮件, 在这里你去, 你可以现在就上网。
And probably find somewhere out there on the net, somebody who will sell you access to computers for cents a piece.
可能会发现在网络上的某个地方, 有人会以几分钱一台的价格向你出售电脑的使用权。
And these are like people's computers like your computer, my computer and Dan says as Darkode got bigger and bigger, he began to see more of this kind of activity on the site, like some guy would have a botnet out of 5000 computers.
这些都是人们的电脑, 如你的电脑, 我的电脑和丹说, 随着Darkode变得越来越大, 他开始看到更多的这种活动的网站上, 像一些家伙会有一个僵尸网络的5000台电脑。
Another guy would have some software like the ransomware. Software guy would then rent the botnet from guy one, install his ransomware
另一个人将有一些软件, 如赎金软件。然后, 软件的家伙会从一个家伙那里租用僵尸网络, 安装他的勒索软件。
Ransom these poor people then move on. You know, some of the people were, you know, doing some pretty unpleasant things, you know.
赎金这些可怜的人, 然后继续前进。你知道, 有些人, 你知道, 做一些相当不愉快的事情, 你知道。
Moving more into the kind of financial crimes territory, which is something that I really never had a desire to be involved in, and it was largely because of that.
更多的是进入金融犯罪领域, 这是我真的从来没有想过要参与的事情, 主要是因为这个原因。
He says that in 2009 he decided to get out.
他说, 在2009年, 他决定退出。
But unfortunately, the next year, I got a lovely visit from the FBI.
但不幸的是, 第二年, 我得到了联邦调查局的一个可爱的访问。
They promptly... Was it like kicked-down-in-your-door type situation? They knocked, they knocked.
他们迅速... 是像踢倒在你的门的类型的情况？他们敲门了, 他们敲门了。
So it what was that like, pretty terrifying.
因此, 它是什么样子的, 相当可怕的。
You know, what's what's gonna happen to me, what's going to happen next? And what did happen next?
你知道, 什么是什么会发生在我身上, 接下来会发生什么？接下来确实发生了什么？
I don't know how much of that I can talk about.
我不知道我可以谈多少这方面的事情。
But I did cooperate with the government, and I have cooperated with them for the last, you know, 5 plus years now. It was a kick in the butt.
但我确实与政府合作了, 而且在过去的五年多时间里, 我一直与他们合作。这是在屁股上踢了一脚。
You know, my parents kinda kicked me out, not that kicked me out, assisted me with a rapid move out. And I've been living on my own since then.
你知道, 我的父母有点把我踢出去, 不是说把我踢出去, 而是协助我迅速搬出去。从那时起, 我一直自己生活。
And ah, became gainfully employed, had a few jobs, um became a little bit more more serious with my then girlfriend, who was now my wife.
而且啊, 变得有收益的就业, 有几份工作, 嗯, 和我当时的女朋友, 也就是现在的妻子, 变得有点更认真了。
So, you know, it's given me an opportunity over the last five years to really make some serious changes to my life.
所以, 你知道, 在过去五年里, 它给了我一个机会, 使我的生活真正有了一些严重的变化。
Meanwhile, over the same five years, Darkode grew into this massive cyber criminals swappy where tens of thousands of stolen social security numbers were bought and sold huge databases of personal information and emails were bought and sold malware and software,
同时, 在同样的五年里, Darkode成长为这个巨大的网络犯罪分子的交换点, 成千上万的被盗社会安全号码被购买和出售巨大的个人信息和电子邮件数据库被购买和出售恶意软件和软件。
various kinds of botnets are sold. And this continued according to Dina Temple-Raston and right up until July 15th of this year, July 15th 2015.
各种各样的僵尸网络被出售。而根据迪娜-坦普尔-拉斯顿的说法, 这种情况一直持续到今年的7月15日, 即2015年7月15日。
Today marks a milestone in our efforts to bring to justice some of the most significant cyber criminals in the world.
今天是我们将世界上最重要的一些网络罪犯绳之以法的努力的一个里程碑。
What ended up happening on July 15th is that the FBI had actually gotten into Darkode with a number of intelligent services from around the world, and they had an 18 month investigation in which they took down in the end,
7月15日最终发生的事情是, 联邦调查局实际上已经与来自世界各地的一些智能服务机构进入了Darkode, 他们进行了18个月的调查, 最后他们拿下了。
28 people. The FBI has effectively smashed the hornet's nest
28人。联邦调查局已经有效地捣毁了大黄蜂的巢穴
and we are in the process of rounding up and charging the hornets.
而我们正在围捕和指控大黄蜂的过程中。
But here's here's what's amazing, right?
但这里是这里是惊人的, 对吗？
So they take down more than two dozen people two weeks later, Darkode is up again.
所以他们拿下了二十几个人两个星期后, Darkode又开始了。
It just pop back up? Just pop back up.
它只是弹回？只是弹回。
Our deep gratitude to NPR's Dina Temple-Raston,
我们对NPR的Dina Temple-Raston深表感谢。
whose reporting really got us going on this whole project, yet props to Kelsey badger to produce her first segment, Danny mills, who produced a second segment.
她的报道真正让我们开始了这个项目, 然而, 支持凯尔西-巴杰制作她的第一个部分, 丹尼-米尔斯, 他制作了第二个部分。
Thanks also to Andrews Ali, Michael Shammos, Gunther Oldman, Monn Leve, Kathy Roder, also Kathy too
还要感谢安德鲁斯-阿里、迈克尔-沙莫斯、冈特-奥德曼、蒙恩-勒夫、凯西-罗德尔, 还有凯西。
don't forget attorney David McCar and the whole crew at the Microsoft Cybercrimes unit, and to you, Robert.
不要忘记大卫-麦卡律师和微软网络犯罪部门的全体人员, 还有你, 罗伯特。
Thank you to you. Why me?  Because you're part of my botnet.
谢谢你。为什么是我？ 因为你是我的僵尸网络的一部分。
I'm Jad  Abrumrad. I'm Robert Krulwich. Thanks for listening.
我是贾德-阿布拉姆拉德。我是罗伯特-克鲁利奇。谢谢你的收听。
Hello, this is Michelle from kaka Hawaii radiolab is supported in part by the Alfred P. Sloan foundation.
你好, 我是卡卡夏威夷电台的米歇尔, 电台部分由阿尔弗雷德-P-斯隆基金会支持。
Enhancing public understanding of science and technology in the modern world. More information about Sloan at www.sloan.org.
加强公众对现代世界的科学和技术的理解。关于斯隆的更多信息, 请访问www.sloan.org。
Science reporting on radiolab is supported in part by Science Sandbox, a Simon's foundation initiative dedicated to engaging everyone with the processes of science.
Radiolab上的科学报道部分由科学沙盒支持, 这是西蒙基金会的一项倡议, 致力于让每个人参与到科学的进程中。
Radiolab was created by Jad Abrumrad and is edited by Soren Wheeler, Lulu Miller and Latif Nasser and co-hosts Susie Luckenbach is our executive producer, and Dylan Keith is a director of sound design.
Radiolab由Jad Abrumrad创建, 由Soren Wheeler、Lulu Miller和Latif Nasser以及共同主持人Susie Luckenbach担任执行制片人, Dylan Keith担任声音设计总监。
Our staff includes Simon Adler, German Bloom, Becca Brussel, Rachel Cusick, Harry Fortuna, David Gabriel, Maria Pasquale
我们的工作人员包括西蒙-阿德勒、德国人布鲁姆、贝卡-布鲁塞尔、雷切尔-库西克、哈利-福图纳、大卫-加布里埃尔、玛丽亚-帕斯夸尔。
Cinderella, [ ... ] and Molly Webster, with help from ..... Our fact-checkers are ...
辛德瑞拉, [......]和莫莉-韦伯斯特, 来自.....。我们的事实核查员是...